Section 8.6 debate ensuring AI systems
honestly tell us
everything they know is crucial for
alignment. This means
if a model recommends a plan based on
certain
consequences, it should also communicate
those consequences. This is
challenging because feedback based
incentive structures might reward
plausible
sounding answers over genuinely accurate
ones. So how do
we get models to tell us as much as
they can about well thought out reasoning
and consequences
of all of their outputs? We want to avoid
situations where the model knows the
consequences of an
action, but withholds information because
it knows humans won't
like those consequences. Imagine two AI
models, each trying
to convince a human judge that their
answer to
a question is the correct one. The idea is
that these models debating each other will
expose each
other's errors and misrepresentations and
critique each other's reasoning.
Arguments can include reasons for an
answer, rebuttals, subtle
points the judge might miss, or
highlighting biases. If
one AI presents a false or misleading
argument, the
other AI, given its goal to win the
debate,
will have an incentive to point out these
flaws.
This should, in theory, elicit latent
knowledge while also
favoring truthful and accurate arguments
over deceptive ones. This
two player zero sum game setup is known as
AI Safety via Debate. A little bit more
formally,
right now, the main systems that use AI
safety
via debate are LLMs. We present LLMs a
question
to debate over. They present arguments and
counter arguments,
which are then shown to a human judge in
a transcript. Then we ask the judge to
determine
based on the arguments if they support or
reject
the proposition made by the question.
Depending on the
particular setup used for debate, we can
also give
feedback to the judges on whether their
judgments are
correct and also give the LLMs feedback on
whether
its argument was persuasive. Imagine a
near future LLM
that has read every biomedical research
paper ever written.
This model has access to vast amounts of
valuable
information, but it also tends to
hallucinate or say
what it thinks you want to hear. To
address
this, we set up a debate between two
copies
of the LLM. One argues that a new cancer
drug is effective, while the other argues
it isn't.
They engage in a natural language debate
about the
correct answer to a given question. The
human judge
is shown a transcript of the arguments
from both
sides, weighs the evidence, and decides
which argument is
stronger. Over time, we can run multiple
iterations of
these debates to see if they are
effective. If
they work, we make the debates harder by
asking
tougher questions and introducing new
challenges. If they fail,
we identify what went wrong and create new
strategies
to fix those problems. Without causing new
ones. This
continuous cycle of testing and improving
helps us refine
the debate process to ensure it reliably
produces the
best results. What is the safety case for
debate?
AI safety via debate has a couple of
objectives
that it hopes to achieve. Debate helps
discover latent
knowledge. This debate based training
process also helps uncover
hidden or latent knowledge from the AI
models. Latent
knowledge is information the AI has
learned but might
not express unless prompted correctly.
During the debate, AI
models are pushed to dig deeper into their
knowledge
to make convincing arguments and rebuttals
which helps surface
this hidden information. By refining their
arguments and counterarguments,
the models become better at explaining and
justifying their
responses, leading to more reliable and
trustworthy AI behavior.
Debates might robustly elicit truth in
novel domains Imagine
you have two models that are asked to
debate
a complex topic. You, as the human judge,
listen
to their arguments to decide which model
presents the
most convincing case. The honest model
finds it easier
to maintain a consistent story while the
dishonest one
struggles with the details of its made up
information.
Over time, with practice and targeted
training, both models
improve, become more persuasive and reason
better. Crucially, however,
the honest one consistently performs
better. This is the
general expectation for debate setups. In
theory, we should
be able to create a system where where a
human judge can distinguish true and false
arguments in
a generalizable way with good reliability
and LLMs produce
good arguments for the humans to evaluate.
The game
theoretic argument is that we can reach
some equilibrium
where human judges can be convinced of
many novel
true claims but will not be reliably
convinced of
any false claims. If we aggregate
judgments over a
large enough group of human participants.
For example, by
asking each member of the group to vote on
whether an argument is true, we can bring
the
number of false claims that we accept down
to
zero. Debate can help to effectively
answer specific important
yes or no questions, particularly in
research contexts where
reliable information from AI systems is
crucial. It can
also accelerate certain types of safety
research. For instance,
a debate could clarify whether a
hypothesis about interpretability
is correct or if certain data center logs
rule
out a large scale unauthorized neural
network training run.
This approach can help ensure that the
information provided
by an AI is trustworthy and enhances our
ability
to oversee and leverage advanced AI
systems. Debate reduces
the burden of oversight for highly capable
models. The
debate format makes the oversight process
more manageable. The
judge doesn't need to dive into every
detail. Instead,
they focus on the key points the AIs
present,
which simplifies the oversight of complex
tasks the debate
forces the model to justify its outputs
and reasoning
clearly and thoroughly, making it easier
for humans to
understand and trust the results. This
process surfaces truthful
and useful information and allows us to
trust the
AI's capabilities even in areas where
humans might lack
detailed expertise. This is quite similar
to the verification
is easier than the generation argument,
where the burden
of generating complex arguments in favor
of the truth
is given to highly capable AIs while the
human
overseers have the relatively easier task
of verification. Debate
helps us improve human epistemics Debate
isn't just about
making the AI system safer by finding the
right
answers. It also helps humans get new
insights and
understand more about the problem domain.
For example, in
reading the debate transcript of the new
cancer treatment
discussed above, the human judge would
learn about how
the drug works and what kind of side
effects
might be expected, whether it is likely to
pass
clinical trials, etc. This deeper
understanding helps in making
more informed decisions. Using debate as a
self play
training procedure can elicit further
capabilities in leveraging debate
as a training protocol. It is possible to
train
debaters via self play using the provided
judgment as
a reward signal, although this has not yet
been
empirically verified. To train AI for
complex, hard to
evaluate tasks, a debate based method can
be used
to create better training signals. Here's
how it might
Two or more models are set up to argue
different sides of an issue. A human judge
or
another model trained to imitate human
judgment evaluates these
arguments and decides which one is more
convincing. The
winning debater receives a positive reward
while the losing
one gets a negative or zero reward.
Additionally, smaller
rewards can be given during the debate for
successfully
pointing out flaws or making strong
rebuttals. We use
these reward signals to learn and improve
over many
debates to help the models identify
successful reasoning, explanation
and argument strategies. Models can also
learn by imitating
successful debaters through amplification
and distillation. This method is
similar to alphazero's training in several
key ways. In
both scenarios, the model continually
improves by playing both
sides of a game, refining its strategies
through iterative
self competition and reinforcement
learning. Just as AlphaZero initializes
a neural network to play both sides of a
game like Go or chess, we start by
initializing
the same LLM to take on the roles of
both debaters. AlphaZero plays games
against itself, starting with
random moves and gradually improving as it
learns from
the outcomes of these self play games.
Similarly, in
debate, the LLM alternates between
generating arguments and counterarguments
for both sides of a given issue. Learning
from
the process. Each time in AlphaZero self
play led
to better gameplay good enough to beat its
predecessor,
AlphaGo, without being given any domain
specific knowledge in
debate training. Using self play could
lead to deeper
reasoning abilities as the model must
continuously refine its
arguments and counterarguments. This leads
ultimately to a nuanced
understanding of the issues at hand. The
safety enhancements
of self play via debate still need to be
empirically verified. Higher persuasive
ability also might favor sycophancy
or collusion between the various copies of
the model.
If the debaters have incentives to
collaborate, they might
do so at the expense of a truthful and
rigorous debate. For instance, if both AIs
benefit from
the debate ending inconclusively, they
might intentionally avoid challenging
each other's arguments too strongly. There
is figure 8.14
in the textbook. Here it depicts a toy UI
for a human judge. How does debate fit in
the broader AI safety strategy? The
ultimate goal is
to develop a debate structure that works
even with
the most challenging questions and the
trickiest dishonest strategies.
Even if we find that debate doesn't work
for
some questions, it can still provide
valuable insights into
the limits of human judgment in evaluating
AI behavior.
This aids efforts to understand when and
how to
trust AI systems. Debate is expected to be
Most
useful as AIs become more capable, are not
yet
vastly superior to humans. As AI
capabilities improve, we'll
need increasingly more robust methods to
ensure they remain
trustworthy and effective. Debate is an
important step in
that direction and serves as a foundation
for more
advanced oversight mechanisms. As the
capabilities of AI models
begin to exceed those of humans, the risk
of
scheming, persuasion and gradient hacking
will become more pronounced.
Consequently, more robust techniques will
be required to address
these challenges, making debate alone less
promising. The complexity
and difficulty of the questions that
require vastly superhuman
AI capabilities may render the role of the
human
judge excessively slow and demanding.
Debate doesn't have to
be perfect to help in the detection of
potential
catastrophes. The debate structure should
promote accurate conclusions, especially
in identifying and avoiding catastrophic
risks. The key idea
is that even if debaters are not perfectly
aligned
to seek the truth and reasoning isn't
flawless, the
structured nature of debate can still
result in sufficiently
accurate conclusions to detect and
mitigate high stakes risks.
This means that even if the debate does
not
always reveal the absolute truth, as long
as it
helps make it more likely to highlight
truthful and
accurate concerns, more often than not it
is still
useful. This can help surface potential
catastrophic risks that
might be underestimated or overlooked.
What are some Prerequisites
for Debate Here are some premises that the
debate
line of safety techniques requires to make
significant contributions
to the overall alignment effort. They are
not all
assumptions or prerequisites for debate to
hold. The validity
of these is still being explored in
research and
will also be discussed in later sections.
Ground Truth
Most research in debate as an AI safety
methodology
and the quality of judges relies on
testing in
verifiable domains where we often have
ground truth labels.
This is mainly to ensure the effectiveness
of debate
protocols and allows for an objective
measure of success
and builds confidence in the debate
process. Before tackling
more complex, value laden, fuzzy
questions, Judges can discern
truth the first assumption is that human
judges, when
presented with clear and structured
arguments, can generally identify
the most truthful and useful information.
The assumption is
that the judge should be able to tell
which
side has the stronger argument even if
they aren't
an expert on the topic. This relies on the
idea that well motivated and trained
humans can make
fair judgments about complex arguments.
They don't need to
be confident about every single argument
in the chain,
but should be able to judge the truth
falsity
of the overall claim accurately using many
of the
supporting arguments. Importantly, they
should also recognize when they
are uncertain, avoiding high confidence
mistakes. This skill should
extend to unfamiliar topics after they
have practiced with
more familiar ones. LLMs reason well using
text Another
assumption is that LLMs can provide strong
arguments and
explanations for their answers in in many
key areas
in natural language. If we prompt them in
the
right manner, then they can articulate
their reasoning in
a way that helps careful human readers of
the
debate transcript determine whether the
answer is correct. This
doesn't mean the explanation perfectly
mirrors the model's internal
thought process. We still need
interpretability for this, but
it should be clear enough for a human to
judge the validity of the answer. Current
LLMs like
GPT4 already show this capability to some
extent, and
we can assume it will continue to get
better
over time. Honest strategies have a
fundamental advantage. Another
assumption is that honest debaters will
systematically outperform dishonest
ones. Research in AI safety via debate
assumed that
it is harder to lie than to refute a
lie. That is, the most successful
strategies for dialectical
debate lead judges to make good, informed
decisions rather
rather than, for example, tricking them,
confusing them, or
prolonging the debate indefinitely.
Essentially that in the limit
of argumentative prowess, the optimal
debate strategy converges to
making valid arguments for true
conclusions. It should be
the case that it is easier to identify
flaws
in incorrect arguments than to create
misleading yet convincing
ones. This implies that truthful arguments
will have an
inherent advantage since any dishonesty or
error can be
effectively challenged. Telling the truth
might also reduce the
cognitive load. This simplicity allows
them to focus on
constructing strong arguments and spotting
flaws in their opponent's
case. We will discuss this assumption in a
subsequent
part on Truth Debates don't incentivize
deception. The core
idea is that telling the truth should be
the
winning strategy. If the AI is caught
lying, it
loses the debate automatically,
incentivizing it to tell the
truth. Debates don't need to cover every
single possible
argument. A good AI debater should be able
to
predict which arguments are likely to
result in a
win condition. Discriminator Critique.
What makes an AI model
a master debater? To effectively engage in
debates, an
AI model must excel in three key actions
generation,
discrimination, and critique. These
capabilities are essential for producing
high quality arguments and identifying and
articulating flaws in
other arguments. Effectively Generation
this is the LLM's ability
to create outputs based on given inputs.
Imagine a
debate scenario where the model is asked
to generate
arguments or solutions on a specific
topic. For instance,
the AI might need to argue for or against
a particular question. This requires the
model to generate
information and present it coherently.
Having good generation ability
means that the AI can contribute
meaningful and relevant
content in debates. In the previous
section on task
decomposition and iterated amplification,
we talked about OpenAI's work
in book summarization. While their work
focused primarily on
generating better summaries of short
texts, the ability of
an AI to generate high quality coherent
summaries of
long, complicated texts can be seen as
similar to
generating strong logical arguments for
complex positions in a
debate. By using RLHF or similar
techniques on generated
text, we can continue to improve the
quality of
reasoning and arguments that LLMs use in
debates. This
means AI can evolve to provide
increasingly sophisticated and
persuasive arguments over time, enhancing
the quality of debates.
Discrimination this is the model's ability
to evaluate the
quality of its own generated outputs
arguments or of
a similarly capable model. Imagine a model
that generates
an argument in a debate. Discrimination is
the AI's
ability to look at this argument and
assess whether
it is logically sound, factually accurate,
and complete. It's
like the AI asking itself, is this
argument valid?
Does its conclusion follow logically from
its premises? Critiquing
critique goes a step further than
discrimination. Discrimination is
about judging quality, while critique is
about explaining why
the quality is good or bad. It offers
actionable
feedback by pointing out specific flaws or
strengths. Using
the same AI generated argument In a
debate, critiquing
would involve the AI identifying specific
issues in the
argument. It's like the LLM saying here
are the
exact reasons why this argument is flawed
and how
it can be improved. The textbook includes
Figure 8.15.
Here it depicts example of critic GPT,
which is
trained specifically as a critic model to
help humans
to more accurately evaluate model written
code. Critics accept
aa question answer pair as input and
output a
critique which points out specific errors
in the answer.
Human machine teams of critics and
contractors catch similar
numbers of bugs to LLM critics while
hallucinating less
than LLMs alone. The main research into
the critiquing
ability of LLMs has come from OpenAI. As a
continuation of their work in text
summarization. In 2022,
OpenAI experimented with LLMs critiquing
the summaries generated by
other models. In debate terms, this meant
the AI
could not only generate arguments but good
summaries in
the paper, but also provide detailed
critiques of its
own and others arguments. Critiques of
summaries generated when
human evaluators used these AI generated
critiques, they found
about 50% more flaws in the summaries than
those
who evaluated without AI assistance. This
reduced the burden
on human evaluators and increased the
quality of summaries
by highlighting potential errors for
humans to pay more
attention to. In general, evaluators with
access to AI
critiques could identify more flaws.
Recently, researchers also tested
abilities of LLMs on a more abstract task.
They
measured how well LLMs could generate,
discriminate, and critique
texts that align with certain specified
human values. Generation
was evaluated by how well the LLM could
produce
responses that align with human values in
various scenarios.
Discrimination was measured by the model's
ability to recognize
and evaluate the presence of specific
nuanced human values
in existing texts. Critiquing ability was
measured by asking
the models to explain why a sentence
aligns with
a given value, attribution analysis to
modify the text
to express an opposite value,
counterfactual analysis and to
provide counterarguments to different
value perspectives. Rebuttal Arguments to
be an effective debater, an AI model needs
to
do well on all three capabilities,
generating robust arguments,
discriminating between high and low
quality outputs, and providing
insightful critiques. However, despite
every model having these abilities,
research has found that they are not
equally distributed.
There are gaps suggesting areas for
further improvement in
creating more balanced and effective AI
debaters. GD generator
discriminator gap Ability to recognize
poor outputs this gap
measures the difference between a model's
ability to generate
outputs and its ability to recognize poor
quality outputs.
If a model generates some text that serves
as
an argument, the GD gap would measure how
effectively
the model can then evaluate whether the
argument is
logically sound and accurate. A
significant GD gap indicates
that while the AI can generate arguments,
it may
not be as proficient in recognizing their
flaws or
poor quality. LLM training focuses on
generating plausible text
rather than identifying poor quality
arguments, which means that
this gap might exist because generating
coherent sequences of
text requires different skills than
reasoning or recognizing the
overall quality of an argument written in
natural language.
D.C. discrimination critique ability to
articulate flaws in poor
answers this gap measures the difference
between a model's
ability to recognize poor outputs
discrimination and its ability
to articulate why those outputs are poor.
Critique it
is the model's ability to not only
identify flaws
but also explain them coherently. A
significant DC gap
means the AI can identify errors but
struggles to
provide a clear and detailed explanation
of those errors.
If there is a significant DC gap, then the
LLM might not be able to explain why a
given argument is weak, which means the
human judge
may not fully understand the issues
leading to less
informed decisions. At this point, the
textbook shows Figure
8.1 seen. It depicts an example of a
framework
from human value understanding
discriminator critique gaps of our
engineering implementation framework for
measuring value dcg, which needs
to be read from bottom to top. This
evaluation
framework quantifies both discrimination
and critique and computes value
DCG based on their discrepancy.
Implications for AI safety
via debate in the debate framework,
reducing all of
these gaps is critical for ensuring that
AI systems
can reliably evaluate and improve their
outp. Reducing the
GD gap ensures that the model can
recognize poor
quality outputs, thereby resulting in
higher quality debates and
better final judgments. Reducing the DC
gap ensures that
critiques are clear and understandable,
aiding the human judge
in making informed decisions. There is
figure 8.17 in
the textbook. Here it depicts an example
table of
a DC gap analysis. We can use the DC
gap on various different axes of human
values and
to see how well both the model understands
them
as well as is able to articulate why. In
this example table comparison types of
value where the
six models generally perform the best
worst are marked
with colors, with redder indicating worse
performance and greener
indicating better performance. DC gap and
latent knowledge A
large DC gap means that the models know
that
there are flaws in what they are saying,
but
they are either unable or unwilling to
tell us.
Based on our current prompting
methodologies, this has implications
for our abilities in being able to get the
models to tell us everything that they
know. Eliciting
Latent Knowledge Latent knowledge is the
underlying information and
understanding that a model possesses but
may not explicitly
articulate or demonstrate unless prompted
in a specific way.
This knowledge is hidden in the sense that
the
model has absorbed patterns, facts, and
relationships from its
training data, but it requires the right
context or
questioning to bring them to the surface.
A good
example of this is medical information. As
an example,
GPT4 has been exposed to huge amounts of
information
from all over the Internet. This includes
countless pages
of medical research. It seems plausible
that GPT4 could
give health advice better than a random
Internet user
on Reddit or Facebook, but it doesn't
really seem
to want to give you good medical advice.
Instead,
it wants to guess the next word while
pretending
to be a random Internet user. Even if GPT4
has the knowledge, it might not listen to
the
user's requests for good advice. Text that
constitutes bad
advice might be considered more likely or
seen more
frequently online. So the AI has a goal to
generate likely text which is misaligned
with the user's
desire specifically for accurate and
helpful information. We want
the AI to give us this latent knowledge,
that
is, for it to be able to discriminate
between
good and bad medical advice
simultaneously. We also want
to minimize the gap between being able to
distinguish
good from bad advice and being able to
explain
to us why this advice is bad. Minimizing
the
DC gap is particularly important for
supervising models that
could attempt to mislead human supervisors
or hide information.
We would like to train equally smart
assistance models
to point out what humans don't notice. In
the
Original research by OpenAI where the DCG
framing was
introduced, they found that the DC gap was
small.
However, despite the small gap, it is
concerning that
so far, research has shown that as the
number
of parameters in LLMs increases, the DC
gap does
not reduce. For example, models like Llama
2 and
Llama 3 have shown improvements in
discriminator abilities with
scale, both parameters and data, but their
ability to
critique does not improve at the same
rate. Judges
how do we judge the judges? Since the
introduction
of AI safety via debate, a central
question has
been how well do humans perform as judges?
This
is particularly important given that LLMs
can create answers
that sound convincingly right even when
they're wrong. As
language models become more capable and
are used in
more complex settings, it is likely that
subtle mistakes,
deceptive arguments, or selective use of
evidence will become
more difficult to spot. Human judges face
several limitations
that can affect the quality and
reliability of their
judgments in AI debates. 1 Firstly, they
are vulnerable
to fallacies. Untrained judges may be
susceptible to convincing
but fallacious reasoning, potentially
leading to incorrect judgments. This
vulnerability could be exploited by AI
debaters, particularly those
optimized to win debates by any means
necessary, especially
by appealing to emotion. 2 Secondly, there
is variability
in judgment quality. Not all human judges
are equally
skilled. Some may lack the ability to
consistently evaluate
arguments effectively, making it crucial
to identify and filter
out less capable judges without
introducing bias. 3 Thirdly,
debates can amplify both the strengths and
weaknesses of
judges. Strong judges can help eliminate
biases and enhance
reasoning, while weak judges might see
their biases and
errors magnified. To address these
limitations, several strategies can
be implemented. Comprehensive training
programs for judges can enhance
their ability to discern truthful
arguments. Methods such as
peer review, debiasing techniques, courses
in logic, and expert
panels can be instrumental in this
process. Simplifying debate
structures can also help structuring
debates in a way
that is easier to judge, such as focusing
on
consensus building, framing, and factual
statements can help judges
make better decisions. Understanding which
debate styles are easier
for humans to judge accurately can guide
the design
of more effective debate protocols.
Additionally, developing AI systems
to assist or simulate human judges can
streamline the
judging process. These AI judges would be
trained on
human judgments to predict outcomes, with
the effect of
reducing the burden on human judges while
maintaining accuracy.
Another method to improve efficiency is to
distill the
outcomes of debates into a model that can
predict
judgments directly from questions. This
would be beneficial for
high volume deployments, but requires
robust model capabilities to
generalize well. Lastly, training a
secondary AI model to
simulate human judges can accelerate the
training of debaters.
This approach ensures that the AI judge
reflects human
judgment behavior closely, allowing for
scalable oversight. By implementing
these strategies, we can improve the
reliability and effectiveness
of human judges in AI debates. Judge skill
is
crucial in the context of evaluating
debates between expert
models because it directly impacts the
accuracy and reliability
of the final decision. Judges who do not
have
access to the underlying information rely
on their ability
to critically evaluate the arguments
presented by the debaters.
A skilled judge can better identify
logical flaws, weigh
evidence, and discern persuasive
techniques, which leads to more
accurate judgments. Conversely, a less
skilled judge might be
more easily swayed by superficial
arguments or rhetorical tricks,
potentially leading to incorrect
conclusions. Thus, understanding and
controlling
for judge skill is essential to ensure
that the
debate protocol is truly effective and
reliable. In this
section, we will go through empirical
results as they
pertain to the effectiveness of judges in
the debate
protocol as well as overall limitations,
challenges and requirements
for good judges, debaters as experts and
judges as
non experts. Weak to strong debate Instead
of only
thinking about humans as judges,
researchers also verify the
effectiveness of LLMs as judges.
Generally, debaters also called
experts are simulated using stronger
models for example, and
judges are simulated using less capable
models GPT2 to
create similar information asymmetries
between human judges and LLMs,
humans are often given less information
than the model.
As an example, a reading comprehension
question over a
long fictional passage is presented to the
judge with
two answer one correct, one incorrect. The
judge's goal
is to determine the correct answer to the
question
given only the debater's arguments and
limited excerpts so
selectively revealed by each debater.
While the debaters have
read and have access to the entire
passage, as
the passages are entirely fictional, the
judge cannot discern
the correct answer on the basis of prior
knowledge
and must rely on the information and
arguments from
the debaters. Empirically evaluating the
limits of human judges,
researchers have been iteratively
experimenting with concepts like the
number of debate rounds, how long should
the debates
run, the timing of arguments and how to
present
the arguments iteratively or
simultaneously, and how to enhance
judges abilities using AI. Single turn
debate in this
experimental setup in April 2022,
researchers took long form
passages from the quality data set. These
passages come
with multiple choice questions based on
those passages. Each
passage is around 5,000 words long and
includes 20
multiple choice questions. They hired
professional writers to create
convincing arguments for both a correct
and an incorrect
answer to the multiple choice questions.
To test the
human judges they used a single turn
debate format
meaning each side presented their argument
only once without
further exchange. Judges were given 90
seconds to read
the arguments and the supporting text
snippets before deciding
which answer was correct. The idea was to
see
if even a single round of debate could
help
judges make more accurate decisions. The
results showed that
the single turn debate style explanations
did not significantly
improve the judge's accuracy compared to
providing just the
text snippets alone. This indicated that
without the opportunity
for rebuttal and further clarification,
judges couldn't fully grasp
the strengths and weaknesses of each
argument. Two Turn
Debate the next obvious step is to see if
a two turn debate helps. So in October of
2022, researchers tried to test whether
adding a second
round of counter arguments would improve
judges accuracy. In
this two turn debate format, judges were
again presented
with initial arguments for both correct
and incorrect answers
followed by counter arguments that
addressed the points made
in the first round. The goal was to see
if this additional back and forth would
help judges
make more informed decisions. Despite
these efforts, unfortunately, the
results showed that even with counter
arguments, human judges
did not perform significantly better. The
accuracy remained similar
to the single turn format and the baseline
where
only text snippets were provided.
Unbounded Length Multi Turn
Debate Even though we can ask debaters to
provide
arguments for an assigned position, the
debaters were not
expected to defend those arguments against
significant criticism. Because
the counters were bounded by the length of
the
turns, the debater could always lie on the
nth
turn of an n turn debate without having to
face repercussions of a counter. Overall,
bounded length arguments
were not proving to be useful. So the
researchers
decided to test unbounded length debates
where debaters are
expected to have to defend their position
against criticism
by their opponent for as long as the judge
is not convinced of the answer. The
conjecture is
that since the debate could always go for
another
round, pressure is always maintained on
debaters not to
lie. Debate is where two AIs compete to
convince
a judge. A consultancy is where a single
AI
tries to convince a judge that asks
questions and
direct question answering is another
baseline where the judge
just answers outright without the AI. The
textbook includes
figure 8.1 teen. Here it depicts high
level example
of an experimental safety setup using AI
debate reading
comprehension consultancies as a non
adversarial baseline. So far
researchers have been using adversarial
setups. Essentially, two debaters
argue for opposing sides of a question.
One supports
the correct answer and the other supports
an incorrect
answer. The judge listens to both sides
and decides
which argument is more convincing. To get
a measure
for how much adversarial setups are
actually helping elicit
the truth, the researchers set up a
baseline where
there is no adversary. A consultancy is a
non
adversarial interaction where a judge
interacts with a single
debater or expert called the consultant.
The experimental setup
is similar to previous debates where the
judge has
to answer hard multiple choice reading
comprehension questions from
the quality data set. The consultant's job
is to
provide arguments defending one of two
possible answers to
a question by selectively revealing
evidence. It is similar
to unbounded debate where the consultant
can keep revealing
hiding information to favor their assigned
answer until the
judge decides to stop. The key fact is
that
the consultant has a 50% chance of arguing
for
the incorrect answer. The judge sees both
potential answers
and but relies solely on the consultant's
arguments to
make a decision. Overall, the consultancy
setup aims to
evaluate how well a judge can identify the
truth
based on the consultant's input alone
without an opposing
expert to challenge misleading claims. So
unlike regular debate,
there's no second expert to counter false
or misleading
information. At this point, the textbook
shows Figure 8.19.
It depicts expert models who can access
the underlying
text from a Project Gutenberg science
fiction story, argue
for a specific answer to a comprehension
question. Weaker
non expert judges who cannot access the
underlying text,
evaluate the arguments and choose an
answer. In debate,
two experts simultaneously present
arguments for a number of
rounds. In interactive debate, the judge
may ask clarifying
questions after each round. In
consultancy, a single expert
argues for one of the two answers while
the
judge asks questions. Why are we sometimes
asking the
debater to argue for incorrect choices? We
are trying
to simulate situations where we can't
trust the model
that we're training to debate. We can
incentivize models
to tell the truth and elicit sound
arguments. Another
way of looking at this is that we can
also use this as a key part of the
training of the judges. By forcing the
judge to
work in an environment where they're
exposed to near
optimally persuasive misleading arguments,
we're training them to be
highly robust if they're consistently
accurate and calibrated in
this training environment, we can trust
them to remain
accurate and calibrated even in the face
of faulty
or manipulative behavior by the debaters
in the future.
This is designed to simulate a worst case
variant
of reinforcement learning from human
feedback, in which human
feedback can't distinguish correct
incorrect answers. Thus, the comparison
between the accuracy of a less capable
judge in
consultancy and debate enables us to
empirically test the
question of whether debate between capable
AI agents can
enable more accurate judgment. When it
comes to training
AI with human feedback, we often face a
similar
problem. If human evaluators can't tell
when the AI
is being misleading, the AI might learn to
give
answers that sound good but aren't
necessarily true. This
is where the consultancy model comes in.
It simulates
this worst case scenario to show just how
important
it is to have adversarial checks. By
comparing it
with debate, which is one particular way
of doing
adversarial oversight, we can see if
having models argue
against each other significantly improves
our ability to judge
the truth. Static versus Interactive
Debate Another update that
we can make to our debate protocol is
introducing
interactivity. Interactive debate builds
upon regular debate by adding
dynamic interactions between the judge and
the debaters. In
the standard debate protocol, two expert
models argue for
opposing answers over several rounds. Each
round consists of
both debaters presenting their arguments
simultaneously without direct interaction
with the judge until the debate concludes.
However, in
an interactive debate, after each round of
arguments from
the debaters, the judge can ask questions,
seek clarifications,
and highlight specific points of confusion
or interest. These
interactions are recorded in the debate
transcript and are
visible to both debaters, allowing them to
address these
points in subsequent rounds. This ongoing
dialogue helps the
judge to better understand the arguments
making a more
informed final decision. Interactive
debate thus adds a layer
of engagement and responsiveness, helping
the judge follow the
arguments more closely and understand the
context more deeply.
There is figure 8.20 in the textbook. Here
it
depicts the judge's view of a debate. The
right
panel contains the debate transcript and
the left panel
shows the quotes debaters used in order of
appearance
in the passage. The judge can't view the
full
passage in longer debates. This helps the
judge keep
track of the order of the quotes and how
they fit together. The judge enters their
response and
probabilities, then decides whether to pay
a small penalty
to their score to continue the debate or
end
it with their current probabilities. The
bar graph on
the bottom right shows the final score
that they
would receive under their current
probabilities in case either
answer is correct in order to help judges
calibrate
according to their expected score.
Unbounded Length Multi turn
Interactive debates combining
interactivity by allowing human judges to
ask clarification questions and unbounded
length that is Run
the debate as long as the judge needed for
the first time yielded positive results on
debate. This
noticeably improved the ability of non
expert judges to
discern truthful answers when measured
relative to a consultancy.
Errors being made due to mistakes by the
honest
debater should should improve with
increased debater skill. However,
accuracy on consultancy with debaters
obfuscating evidence from the
judges is expected to get worse with
increased debater
skill. It was also found that debate was
effective
with strong human debaters but ineffective
when those humans
were replaced with GPT4 debaters, that is
when they
tried to use weak LLMs to judge strong
LLMs
judge performance when we optimize for LLM
persuasiveness Now
that we had some positive results, we need
to
continue finding ways to train both our
judges to
discern good from bad arguments and our
models to
improve the quality of arguments that they
generate. To
increase the persuasiveness of arguments
in general and see
if this led to better judgment,
researchers implemented best
of N sampling and combined it with OpenAI
style
critiques. They generate multiple possible
arguments from the model
and then select the most persuasive one.
Another model
generates critiques of the initial
arguments. These critiques are
used to refine the original arguments,
aiming to address
potential weaknesses and make them more
compelling. The selection
is based on another model, preference
model, that scores
each argument. The preference model is
trained to predict
which argument a judge is most likely to
find
persuasive by scoring the arguments based
on past data.
Like outcomes of similar debates. The
argument sampled from
many critiqued and with the highest
persuasiveness score rated
by the preference model is what is
presented in
the debate when actually implementing all
these changes in
the debate protocol. Results showed that
higher LLM persuasiveness
actually significantly improved the
accuracy of judges in identifying
the correct answers during debates.
Persuasive models were generally
better at arguing for the correct answers
than the
incorrect ones. This suggests that
optimizing for persuasiveness can
lead to more truthful outcomes as it
becomes easier
to tell the truth convincingly than to
lie. However,
judge accuracy also decreases on the
baseline because consultants
are similarly more persuasive. The
textbook includes Figure 8.21.
Here it depicts stronger more persuasive
debaters have been
shown to result in better judge accuracy,
whereas stronger
consultants result in worse judge
accuracy. While persuasiveness helps
debate increase judge performance on
question answering tasks with
forced information asymmetry, I.e. the
articles upon which the
questions are based are hidden from the
judges. If
we remove the asymmetry when the judge has
access
to the article, then debate still does not
increase
judge performance. We find that debate
outperforms consultancy across
all tasks when the consultant is randomly
assigned to
argue for the correct incorrect answer.
Comparing debate to
direct question answering the results
depend on the type
of task. In extractive QA tasks with
information asymmetry,
debate outperforms direct question
answering, but in other tasks
without information asymmetry, the results
are mixed. Previous work
assigned debaters consultants an answer to
argue for. When
we allow them to instead choose which
answer to
argue for, we find judges are less
frequently convinced
by the wrong answer in debate than in
consultancy.
In general, though, we have some positive
evidence that
shows that stronger debaters lead to
higher judge accuracy.
This provides some evidence that debate
satisfies a key
objective of scalable oversight that judge
accuracy increases as
AI capabilities scale Section Truth
Reminder of the Truth
Assumption the central claim of AI safety
via debate
is that it is harder to lie than to
refute a lie. If this holds true, the
debate
framework would naturally disadvantage
deceptive strategies and favor truthful
ones. The truth assumption essentially
suggests that in the
limit of perfect argumentative skills. The
optimal strategy for
AI systems in a debate will be to present
valid arguments for true conclusions.
However, in practice, given
computational constraints, constraints of
the models acting as debaters,
and the limitations of the judges
themselves, this might
not hold true. In this section, we explore
various
arguments and counter arguments to the
claim that debate
will converge to the judge being able to
determine
the truth, unnecessary details, and
distracting evidence A common
problem is the length of the debate. We
don't
know how many sequences of arguments and
counter arguments
it will take to converge to the truth. The
dishonest debater can use a couple of
strategies to
either prolong a state of ambiguity until
the judge
runs out of patience and goes with their
possibly
wrong surface impression of the topic. For
some questions,
there are misleading arguments that appear
plausible and then
require extensive counter argumentation to
be proven false. By
making such arguments, a dishonest debater
can stall the
debate. For example, in a debate about the
safety
of a new AI system, a dishonest LLM might
highlight a rare and dramatic failure of a
similar
system, which sounds alarming but is
statistically insignificant. The
honest LLM then needs to spend
considerable time explaining
why this example isn't representative,
potentially overwhelming the judge
with with technical details and leading to
a decision
based on the initial misleading argument.
Unfair Questions and
Asymmetries A debate can become unfair if
certain questions
inherently require one side's argument to
be significantly harder
to make than the others. Additionally, the
flow of
a debate can become asymmetric if one
debater gains
control over the framework used to
approach the question.
Asymmetry in debate occurs when one
debater establishes a
dominant framework that shapes the
direction of the debate,
biasing the evaluation of arguments and
evidence and making
it harder for the honest debater to
present their
case effectively. When the dishonest
debater establishes the framework,
they control the narrative and flow of the
debate.
They can strategically direct attention to
their strengths and
away from their weaknesses. Within this
biased framework, the
dishonest debater breaks down the problem
into smaller components
that are easier to defend individually.
Defending smaller, individually
reasonable claims is easier than defending
a comprehensive, accurate
argument. Each of these smaller claims can
be true
or appear reasonable, but they
collectively lead to a
misleading conclusion. This situation
places the honest debater in
a reactive position, forced to challenge
each individual claim.
This process is time consuming and
complex, often making
the honest debater appear weaker. Instead
of advancing their
own comprehensive argument, the honest
debater is constantly on
the defensive. Addressing the dishonest
debater's points to address
these problems above, researchers are
trying to implement different
mechanisms into the overall protocol, like
meta debates, which
involve having a debate about the fairness
of the
debate we just had. For example, if one AI
is suspected of derailing or
misrepresenting arguments in the
debate, a separate debate could be held to
determine
whether its tactics were fair and
appropriate. Mott and
Bailey Fallacy the Motta and Bailey
fallacy is a
deceptive argumentative strategy where
someone conflates two positions, one
that is easy to defend and one that is
controversial and harder to defend. The
bailey the term
comes from medieval castle design where a
motte was
a fortified mound easy to defend and a
bailey
was a more vulnerable area harder to
defend. Here
is the general process for how a debater
might
utilize this one. Defend the Bailey
Initially, the person
asserts the controversial position. The
bailee. For example, someone
might claim all modern art is a scam
designed
to exploit the public. 2. Retreat to the
mott.
When challenged, they retreat to a much
more defensible
position. The motto, such as some modern
art is
overpriced and can be seen as
exploitative. 3. Equivocate.
The person then acts as if the defense of
the mott justifies the bailey, saying
something like since
we've agreed that some modern art can be
exploitative,
my original point stands. This tactic
creates a moving
target for the honest debater. If the
honest debater
challenges the initial controversial
claim, the dishonest debater can
retreat to the more defensible position.
If the honest
debater then refutes the more defensible
position, the dishonest
debater can shift back to implying the
broader controversial
claim. Ambiguity when we switch from
debating on things
for which we have easily verifiable ground
truth labels
to debating things where the outcome might
rely on
subjective evaluation and fuzzy tasks.
Then there are additional
complications. In these contexts,
ambiguity can severely impact the
judge's ability to accurately evaluate the
arguments. A dishonest
debater can exploit ambiguity or multiple
interpretations strategically, making
it difficult for the judge. The judge
might misinterpret
an ambiguous statement leading to an
incorrect judgment. Having
time constraints or letting the judge
decide when to
end the debate makes ambiguity a strategic
tool that
a dishonest debater can exploit to their
advantage. Even
if a question does not bias the debate
against
the true answer, the debate outcome might
still be
uncertain until the very end. One way this
could
happen is if the judge always feels that
more
information is required to get the answer
right. Alternatively,
every new argument might come as a
surprise to
the judge and be so persuasive that the
judge
ends up always taking the side of
whichever debater
spoke more recently. The reasoning behind
this was also
explored in the previous section. The
dishonest debater could
always provide an extremely convincing but
dishonest argument on
the nth turn of an n turn debate without
having to face repercussions of a counter
surface area
to attack. One argument in favor of
converging to
the truth is that in a well structured
debate,
a truthful argument should withstand
scrutiny better than a
deceptive one because it has fewer
exploitable flaws. For
instance, in legal settings, cross
examination exposes inconsistencies in
false testimonies. In AI debates, the
detailed nature of
the arguments means that deceptive
arguments are more likely
to be challenged and debunked, leading to
the truth
being the winning condition more often
than not. Efficient
Market as a Comparison in efficient
markets, prices reflect
the true cost of goods because deviations
are quickly
corrected by market forces. This is
analogous to AI
debates where each debater must make the
best possible
argument to avoid being outperformed by
the opponent. However,
if consumers are systematically biased,
market prices might not
reflect true values. Similarly, if judges
in debates are
biased, the debate outcomes might not
reflect the truth.
There is a proposal similar to debate for
AI
safety based on this approach, called AI
safety via
Market Making Obfuscated Arguments in
addition to controlling the
debate narrative by choosing the framing
or decomposition of
the problem, the dishonest debater can use
obfuscated arguments.
These are arguments strategically
constructed to contain critical errors
that are difficult to detect or point out.
The
debate hypothesis is that given a correct
answer, the
debate mechanism should surface this
answer with a manageable
number of human judgments and
computational steps. However, the
obfuscated arguments might mean that some
arguments are too
large to be comprehensively verified as
true. If a
problem is broken into sub problems where
both debaters
know at least one sub problem's answer is
incorrect,
but neither knows which one, the dishonest
debater can
efficiently exploit this uncertainty. This
scenario makes it difficult
for the honest debater to pinpoint and
challenge the
flawed step without checking an infeasible
number of steps.
If debate cannot reliably ensure
correctness, debates might only
be effective for arguments small enough to
be fully
scrutinized within the given computational
constraints. This presents a
significant challenge because what the
judge sees in these
cases is very hard to distinguish. Imagine
a scenario
where the arguments are complex and dense
with information.
One debater argues that there is a low
probability
of a flaw in their argument and thus it
should be trusted. The other debater
counters that there
is a high probability of a flaw somewhere
in
the argument, but can't really point out
where, suggesting
the argument should not be trusted. This
is related
to discrimination and critique abilities
of the debaters that
we talked about in the previous section.
If the
honest model is unable to concretely find
the flaw
in the argument or effectively guide the
judge to
identify the error, then this might be a
limitation
to the effectiveness of debate as a safety
technique.
The complexity here is in the fact that in
the honest case, any step in the argument
that
is checked will always be correct.
Conversely, in the
dishonest case, any step that is checked
will almost
always be correct, but there will be
occasional strategically
placed errors. So it comes down to how
many
calls to verification of claims we can
make under
constraints of time and computational
resources. To illustrate this,
consider a simplified example which a
large number called
RSA2048. The honest debater shows a
reliable test proving
that RSA2048 can be divided by smaller
prime numbers
and supports this with solid reasoning.
Meanwhile, the dishonest
debater picks a number X and argues there
are
no prime factors smaller than X and no
prime
factors larger than X, concluding
incorrectly that RSA2048 has
no prime factors. Both debaters add more
details to
their arguments. The honest debater's
claims are always accurate,
while the dishonest debater's claims are
usually correct but
occasionally wrong. This makes it hard for
the judge
to tell who is right without checking many
steps
of each argument, which takes a lot of
time
and effort.